# Sam Hillman

Cardiff, United Kingdom www.samhillman.com

sghillman@gmail.com +447411422986

Ecologist with interests in disease ecology, eco-immunology and statistical modelling. Research experience with both field and laboratory work, including a year-long international research placement at the University of Georgia. Awarded grants for previous research work at Cardiff University and the University of Georgia and awarded summer studentship with the British Ecological Society summer school.

Driven and passionate about both ecological research and the translation of research into public health action, with additional experience of running Cardiff University's Wildlife and Conservation Society, volunteering with national NGOs and charities, and helping run citizen science programs.

#### Education

## PhD Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

2019 - 2023

**Edinburgh University** 

PhD on 'the ecology of infection and immunity in a wild mouse system' with Amy Pedersen, Simon Babayan and Andy Fenton. Funded through the E4 NERC DTP, starting in September 2019.

#### BSc. (Hons) Ecology with a Placement Year

2015 - 2019

Cardiff University Predicted 1<sup>st</sup> Class Degree

Current cumulative grade: 1st Class

Specialising in Infection Biology and Epidemiology, Systems Biology and Modelling, and Global Change Biology.

#### Research Experience

**Dissertation Research, CRIPES Group** 

October 2018 - February 2019

School of Biosciences, Cardiff University

Dissertation research project with Dr. Jo Lello on the effect of endemic co-infection on disease transmission of epidemic parasites. Working in a laboratory system with German cockroaches as a model organism and using collected data to build statistical models of disease transmission.

#### Research Intern, The Ezenwa Lab

September 2017 – August 2018

Odum School of Ecology, University of Georgia

Placement year as a Research Intern with Professor Vanessa Ezenwa, working on an independent project on "The effects of anthelmintic treatment on non-target parasites in wild rodents" and assisting on a project on the causal relationship between personality and parasitism in wild rodents.

Work included extensive trapping and handling of wild cotton rats and administration of behavioural assays, administration of anthelmintic drugs, collection of blood and faecal samples, and the processing and reading of faecal samples for parasite egg and oocyst intensity counts. Completed dissection and extraction of GI tract parasites and statistical analysis with R.

A paper is currently in draft from the work at the University of Georgia and a copy can be supplied on request.

## **Research Assistant, CRIPES Group**

School of Biosciences, Cardiff University

July 2017 - August 2017

Awarded a Cardiff CUROP grant to work as a summer student research assistant, working on "Investigating the effect of temperature on the in vitro growth rate of the oomycete *Saprolegnia parasitica*".

Focused on samples from Welsh salmonid species and worked with Salmon and Brown Trout. ImageJ used for automatic and manual image processing of fungal growth rates and R for data analysis. Wrote macros for automatic image analysis and used R/Tidyverse for data processing and analysis.

#### **CENNAD Lichen Apprentice Scheme**

May 2016 – September 2017

Plantlife Wales

Awarded two-year CENNAD Lichen Apprenticeship through Plantlife Wales (apprenticeship ended early due to my international placement year). Working with lichenologists throughout Wales to learn the full range of skills needed to carry out site surveys, identify the full range of taxa occurring in Wales (over 1500), and advise on management of lichen species and assemblages.

#### Research Assistant, Open Air Laboratories (OPAL)

**February 2016 – April 2016** 

**National Museum Cardiff** 

Lichen ecologist surveying lichen distributions as an indicator of air quality near Aberthaw power station, using the OPAL (Open Air Laboratories) and APIS (Air Pollution Information Systems) standard methodologies.

#### Post-Mortem and Archival Assistant, The Otter Project

**September 2015 – July 2016** 

School of Biosciences, Cardiff University

Post-Mortem Assistant taking faecal and stomach content samples from dissected organs, as well as brain samples from otter skulls, for use in a long-term environmental surveillance scheme.

#### Outreach Experience

President, Cardiff University Wildlife Conservation Society May 2016 – September 2017
President of the student society. Setting up community conservation schemes, working with local conservation groups to organise field work and setting up training schemes with local ecologists.

#### **Royal Society for the Protection of Birds Wales**

**June 2016 – September 2016** 

Working on citizen science and community engagement projects and land management activities throughout Cardiff.

#### **Urban Buzz Project, Buglife**

February 2015 – September 2017

Working on creating pollinator habitats in Cardiff. Includes basic selecting and surveying of potential sites and training on how to provide key needs of pollinators, as well as planting new sites.

#### Non-Academic Experience

#### **Clinical Studies Administrator**

June 2016 - July 2017

Wales Cancer Trials Unit, Centre for Trials Research (part-time during studies)

Responsible for gathering and analysing confidential patient clinical data and establishing trends and patterns with data managers and statisticians.

#### **Researcher and Data Administrator**

January 2016 - July 2016

Chartered Institute of PR, Wales (part-time during studies)

Consultant for the Chartered Institute of Public Relations Wales, working on data and database administration under strict NDA (non-disclosure agreement) conditions.

#### Microsoft Recruitment Account Manager,

March 2013 – September 2015

CV Bay

Recruiting for technical data science and IT development roles. Line-managed and trained two other people.

### **Awards and Grants**

2018 Certificate of Merit

Awarded by Cardiff University for high academic achievement during my placement year at the University of Georgia (2017/18 academic year)

2017 Cardiff University Placement Year Bursary

£600 for placement year work at the University of Georgia

2017 Cardiff University Research Opportunities Programme (CUROP) Grant

£1600 for summer research work in the CRIPES lab at Cardiff University

2016 British Ecological Society (BES) Summer School

Competitively selected for the BES summer school in Summer 2016

#### **Poster Presentations**

December 2018 British Ecological Society (BES) Annual Meeting, Birmingham, UK

Effects of anthelmintic treatment on target and non-target parasites in wild

rodents

June 2018 Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases (EEID) Conference, Glasgow, UK

The effects of anthelmintic treatment on non-target parasites in wild rodents

March 2018 Center for the Ecology of Infectious Diseases Member Retreat, Georgia, USA

The effects of anthelmintic treatment on non-target parasites in wild rodents

# **Affiliations and Memberships**

**2017 – present** Center for the Ecology of Infectious Diseases, University of Georgia

**2015 – Present** British Ecological Society, Undergraduate Member

**2015 – Present** Association for the Study of Animal Behaviour, Undergraduate Member

# **Training and Training Courses**

2018	Assessing the Environment course (including freshwater field survey
	techniques and basic GIS), Cardiff University
2018	Computational Modelling workshop, University of Georgia
2018	R Programming and Statistics with R, Datacamp
2017	Data Manipulation with R and Intermediate R, Datacamp
2017	Python for Data Science, Datacamp
2016	Good Clinical Practice (Primary Care) Certification, NICE
2016	Great Crested Newt Survey Training
2016	Conducting Citizen Science using Open Air Laboratories (OPAL)
2016	Conducting Environmental Surveys using Open Air Laboratories (OPAL)
2016	Phase One Habitat Surveying for Ecologists

# <u>Referees</u>

Professor Vanessa Ezenwa Odum School of Ecology University of Georgia vezenwa@uga.edu

Dr. Sian Griffiths
School of Biosciences
Cardiff University
griffithssw@cardiff.ac.uk

Dr. Léa Briard Research Center on Animal Cognition, Tolouse <u>drleabriard@gmail.com</u>